<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chromatic homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/chromatic-homotopy-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chromatic homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/chromatic-homotopy-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Exotic algebraic models</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2024/exotic-algebraic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2024/exotic-algebraic-models/</guid>
      <description>As has been the case a couple of times already, when faced with an increased workload I tend to neglect writing on this blog. It is only natural that increased amounts of work in one section lead to a decreased amount of work in another — there is, after all, only a finite amount of time given to us. But, for the remainder of my PhD I will solely focus on research and outreach, hence I will hopefully have some more time to write and think.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chromatic redshift</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/chromatic-redshift/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/chromatic-redshift/</guid>
      <description>In a recent lunch conversation with Nils Baas we, among a plethora of other things, discussed the chromatic redshift phenomenon in stable homotopy theory. Nils was explaining some things about the results he had published together with Bjørn Dundas and John Rognes on using $2$-vector bundles to explain the algebraic K-theory of topological K-theory, i.e. $K(ku)$. This spectrum has height $2$, and since $ku$ has height $1$ this exhibits a phenomenon called redshift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Periodic torsion is torsion periodic</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/periodic-torsion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/periodic-torsion/</guid>
      <description>Hi, long time no see. I used to be very persistent about writing at least one blog-post each month, but as one can see, I have taken a break for a couple months due to vacation and increased teaching and lecturing duties at NTNU. Incidentally it coincided exactly with the 2 year mark of having posted at least once a month, often more. I have been writing stuff, but not anything worth posting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
