<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stable homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/stable-homotopy-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stable homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/stable-homotopy-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Adapted homology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/adapted-homology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/adapted-homology/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In the last post we studied homology theories as abstract functors from stable $\infty$-categories to abelian categories. We showed that for every stable $\infty$-category $\mathcal{C}$ there is a universal homology theory which all others factor through, namely the Yoneda embedding into the Freyd envelope,
$$ y\colon \mathcal{C}\longrightarrow A(\mathcal{C}). $$
The fact that this is universal means that for any homology theory $H\colon \mathcal{C}\longrightarrow \mathcal{A}$ there is an essentially unique factorization</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universal homology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/universal-homology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/universal-homology/</guid>
      <description>New year; same me; new math. During the fall I said that I wanted to post on this blog monthly, but that did not happen for some reason. I thought I’d try again this semester, but maybe I am setting this not that high bar still too high for my self. For some reason there seems to be fewer hours in the day than it used to. The cover page for the post is generated by Dalle·2 using the prompt &amp;ldquo;A man finding the universal piece, old painting&amp;rdquo; – a true work of art.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Johnson-Wilson theory</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/johnson-wilson-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/johnson-wilson-theory/</guid>
      <description>It has been some time since we studied at the correlation between formal group laws, which were certain power series that looked like Taylor expansion of multiplication on a Lie group, and complex oriented cohomology theories. In particular, we learned that these two completely separate notions had a common universal object. The universal formal group law over the Lazard ring was the same as the formal group law determined by the universal complex oriented cohomology theory — complex cobordism cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stable infinity-categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/stable-infinity-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/stable-infinity-categories/</guid>
      <description>This semester I am taking part in a seminar on $\infty$-categories, administered by Rune Haugseng. So far we have covered roughly: the basic definitions, fibrations, limits, colimits, Joyal’s lifting theorem, equivalences, straightening, Yoneda lemma, adjunctions and Kan extensions. This week it is my turn to give a talk on stable $\infty$-categories, and this blog post will hopefully be some sort of lecture notes for this talk. The intersection of things in this post and the contents of the talk should at least be non-empty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Adams spectral sequence</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/the-adams-spectral-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/the-adams-spectral-sequence/</guid>
      <description>Recently my friend Elias started his own math blog adventure, and his first post gave a nice introduction to spectral sequences. Reading it I remembered that I should really understand some of the parts better myself, because a lot of the arguments one makes in chromatic homotopy theory are based on spectral sequences. There is a framework for constructing spectral sequences that are not covered in my old post on them, as well as Elias’ post, and that is creating spectral sequences from exact couples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brown-Peterson cohomology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/brown-peterson-cohomology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/brown-peterson-cohomology/</guid>
      <description>Over the holidays sadly Edgar H. Brown passed away. He was one of the influential men behind many of the concepts this blog has featured and will feature in the future. This post is in particular focused on one of these concepts, namely Brown-Peterson cohomology and the Brown-Peterson spectrum.
In the last post we developed the category of $p$-local spectra, and in the post before that we explored complex cobordism cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bousfield localization</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/bousfield-localization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/bousfield-localization/</guid>
      <description>Topology, particularly homotopy theory, is hard. The scenes where these kind of mathematics happen are immensely complicated; the category of topological spaces; the category of spectra. The problem is that there is simply too much information to try to capture by using simple tools that we can actually understand properly. Trying to classify topological spaces or spectra is a feat that many deem impossible, it is simply too difficult.
So, how can we try to fix this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex cobordism cohomology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/complex-cobordism-cohomology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/complex-cobordism-cohomology/</guid>
      <description>In the next couple years I will need to understand the ins and outs of different cohomology theories and the spectra that represents them. Some of the most important of these (for my research) can be described using $MU$ — the complex cobordism spectrum. We briefly met this spectrum — or at least its cohomology theory — when we discussed formal group laws. There we explained briefly a theorem of Quillen, stating that the universal formal group law over the Lazard ring corresponds to complex cobordism cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The homotopy groups of the spheres. Part 2</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-groups-of-spheres-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-groups-of-spheres-2/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post we studied some &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; cases of homotopy groups of spheres. We focused most on the group $\pi_3(S^2)$ and its computation from the Hopf fibration. All groups calculated last time were part of the so-called unstable range, meaning that they are not invariant under suspension. Due to the Freudenthal suspension theorem we know precicely the stable range for homotopy groups of spheres, and these are given by the stable homotopy groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The stable homotopy category</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-stable-homotopy-category/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-stable-homotopy-category/</guid>
      <description>A little while ago we discussed the definition of a tensor triangulated category, and in that post we mentioned an example that we didn&amp;rsquo;t explicitly define, namely the stable homotopy category. The goal for todays post is to fix this. There are many ways of defining it, and some are actually better than others. As the name suggests, the stable homotopy category is a homotopy category, which we have discussed before in the fibration series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stable homotopy</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/stable-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/stable-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>For the last few posts we have covered some theory surrounding cohomology theories, and today we want to do something else, namely again look at some homotopy theory. It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since we have covered homotopy groups, but today we return once again. In particular I want to cover a theorem and its consequences — the Freudenthal suspension theorem. This is one of the central theorems in the homotopy theory of topological spaces, and is one of the more important theorems we left out from the fibration series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formal group laws</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/formal-group-laws/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/formal-group-laws/</guid>
      <description>Recently we have covered a lot of heavy topology and abstract mathematics, so today I thought we would cover something else — something maybe a bit easier to grasp. We will introduce the concept of formal group laws, and a bit on why they are interesting.
Introduction and definition To not just spew out the definition straight away, we look at a situation where formal group laws arise very naturally. Let $G$ be a one-dimensional commutative Lie group (Think here of the real numbers $\mathbb{R}$ or the circle group $S^1$).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A first look at spectra</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-first-look-at-spectra/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-first-look-at-spectra/</guid>
      <description>Even though this blog is not centered around a specific topic, we have during the last year looked more frequently at certain topics than others, such as (co)homology theory, homotopy theory and category theory. We will continue this trend today as we will try to find a solid reason for a particular object to exist. These objects were briefly mentioned in the earlier post on tensor triangulated categories, namely spectra. These objects are hugely important to the field of algebraic topology, one reason being that they are intimately linked to cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor triangulated categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/tensor-triangulated-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/tensor-triangulated-categories/</guid>
      <description>For the last five years mathematics has been my passion, as well as my main focus in life. This passion for mathematics will hopefully not diminish, as I am now heading into four more years of studies and research through a PhD in mathematics at NTNU. I am joining a project, called Tensor triangulated geometry in Trondheim, so today I thought I would explore the definition of one of the main players in this theory, namely tensor triangulated categories.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
