<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stable homotopy</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/stable-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/stable-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>For the last few posts we have covered some theory surrounding cohomology theories, and today we want to do something else, namely again look at some homotopy theory. It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since we have covered homotopy groups, but today we return once again. In particular I want to cover a theorem and its consequences — the Freudenthal suspension theorem. This is one of the central theorems in the homotopy theory of topological spaces, and is one of the more important theorems we left out from the fibration series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formal group laws</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/formal-group-laws/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/formal-group-laws/</guid>
      <description>Recently we have covered a lot of heavy topology and abstract mathematics, so today I thought we would cover something else — something maybe a bit easier to grasp. We will introduce the concept of formal group laws, and a bit on why they are interesting.
Introduction and definition To not just spew out the definition straight away, we look at a situation where formal group laws arise very naturally. Let $G$ be a one-dimensional commutative Lie group (Think here of the real numbers $\mathbb{R}$ or the circle group $S^1$).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A first look at spectra</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-first-look-at-spectra/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-first-look-at-spectra/</guid>
      <description>Even though this blog is not centered around a specific topic, we have during the last year looked more frequently at certain topics than others, such as (co)homology theory, homotopy theory and category theory. We will continue this trend today as we will try to find a solid reason for a particular object to exist. These objects were briefly mentioned in the earlier post on tensor triangulated categories, namely spectra. These objects are hugely important to the field of algebraic topology, one reason being that they are intimately linked to cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Traveling</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/traveling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/traveling/</guid>
      <description>How can we use travel-journaling to study some highly abstract and highly complicated mathematical machinery? Can we get anything out of such an analogy? In this post we do just that, study the homotopy hypothesis and infinity groupoids through the lens of a travel ledger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On formal DG-algebras</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/on-formal-dg-algebras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/on-formal-dg-algebras/</guid>
      <description>I have recently handed in and defended my master thesis in mathematics, so I though I would go through its abstract and try to explain what it&amp;rsquo;s all about. We look at formality of DG-algebras, Massey products, A_infinity-algebras and how we can use these to some interesting results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor triangulated categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/tensor-triangulated-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/tensor-triangulated-categories/</guid>
      <description>For the last five years mathematics has been my passion, as well as my main focus in life. This passion for mathematics will hopefully not diminish, as I am now heading into four more years of studies and research through a PhD in mathematics at NTNU. I am joining a project, called Tensor triangulated geometry in Trondheim, so today I thought I would explore the definition of one of the main players in this theory, namely tensor triangulated categories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated geometric intuition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/updated-geometric-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/updated-geometric-intuition/</guid>
      <description>The first post on this blog is titled &amp;ldquo;geometric intuition&amp;rdquo;, and discusses the geometry behind Noether&amp;rsquo;s normalization lemma. When I wrote it I didn&amp;rsquo;t yet understand all the pieces, as I was not very comfortable working with algebraic geometry. One year later, I&amp;rsquo;m still not comfortable, but a bit more than last year. So, I thought I would update last years post with my new knowledge, as well as generalize the intuition to schemes - which we introduced in the last post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schemes</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/schemes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/schemes/</guid>
      <description>The first two posts ([1],[2]) I ever did on this blog - now over a year ago - were posts about algebraic geometry. In particular we explored the geometric implications of some of the algebraic results I was learning in my commutative algebra class. Last summer I also wrote a post about sheaves, and left it off by claiming to soon write about schemes. If you scroll through the blog we have covered a bunch of different topics, but the blog post on schemes, seems to have fallen through the cracks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sha-algebras</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/sha-algebras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/sha-algebras/</guid>
      <description>This is part four in a sort of connected story about operations in mathematics that are associative up to homotopy. It will probably be beneficial to read part 1, part 2 and part 3 in advance of this, but it is not required in theory. These previous posts do however build up some intuition and motivation for the object we are looking at today. To quickly recap what we already seen in these previous posts we recall that we started out by looking at how to transfer a group structure on a topological space through an isomorphism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The associating homotopy</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>In the two last posts we have been discussing operations that are associative up to homotopy, and where such operations might arise naturally in topology. One claim I made, which I later realized was maybe a bit unmotivated and in need of some clarification was how some higher arity maps actually defined (or were defined by) homotopies between combinations of the lower arity maps. We also purely looked at this in a topological setting, but in algebraic topology we often translate to algebraic structures, so I also wanted to see clearly that the same constructions hold in that setting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaces with operations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/spaces-with-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/spaces-with-operations/</guid>
      <description>In the most recent blog post we discussed homotopy associativity and how to transfer algebraic structures on topological spaces. There we in particular used topological groups, which are topological spaces with group structures. That said, any group is a topological group by equipping it with the discrete topology. So if we want to study some actual topology, and not just glorified group theory, we need to look at where multiplications and binary operations arise naturally in topology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy associativity</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</guid>
      <description>Imagine we have a system of two topological spaces $f:T\longrightarrow G$. We are often interested in knowing if a certain property on the space $G$ can be transferred through f such that we have the same property on $T$. If f is a nice enough morphism an example could be a topological invariant of $G$, for example its Euler characteristic. In this post we are more interested in transferring other things than invariants, more specifically structures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A lecture in my second year</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-lecture-in-my-second-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/a-lecture-in-my-second-year/</guid>
      <description>For those that don’t know I am a fifth year mathematics student at NTNU, meaning I am finishing my masters degree after this semester. During my time at NTNU I have had some wonderful classes, and some wonderful teachers. Since most I post about on this blog is related to topology, it is very safe to assume that some of my most memorable courses are exactly the topology courses. I very recently looked at my notes from my first topology course, or rather one of the two first, as I took two in parallel during my fourth semester.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanging pictures with knots</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/hanging-pictures-with-knots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/hanging-pictures-with-knots/</guid>
      <description>Last year I posted a blog post where we looked at a way to use elementary homotopy theory to hang a picture on the wall in a stupid way. The task was to hang a picture on two nails in such a way that if we pull one of the nails out, the picture falls down. “That is stupid” I hear you say, but premise is as premise does, or something similar quoted from Forrest Gump.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are there knots?</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/there-are-knots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/there-are-knots/</guid>
      <description>Something I have been looking into a bit lately, due to it sadly not being taught at my university is knot theory. This is something I have always known to be a part of topology, and have known to have interesting applications in physics, medicine, chemistry and more. So to rectify the situation I thought I would prove that knots exist. It was also nice to take a brake from all the higher category theory we have been looking into lately!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/quasi-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/quasi-categories/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago I held a talk on introductory higher category theory. Most of the talk was based upon thing we already have discussed on this blog, such as the strict $2$-category $Cat$, bicategories, and why strictness fails for the category of topological spaces. The inly thing I talked about which I haven’t yet featured on this blog is the notion of quasi-categories, so I though that I would do that today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vertical monoids</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/vertical-monoids/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/vertical-monoids/</guid>
      <description>You may be thinking, what the heck is a monoid, and why the heck is it vertical? To explain this we will need some insight into classical categories and $2$-categories, which we luckily have been developing for the last few posts. First off, to let the familiar readers know, the objects of study today is called monads, not vertical monoids. But, I like to visualize them and think about them as somehow vertical, or at least something not strictly horizontal or one-dimensional.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/equivalences-of-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/equivalences-of-categories/</guid>
      <description>Last fall I held a talk about functors, natural transformations and equivalences of categories. This talk was part two of five in a student seminar on introductory category theory. There was mostly second year students attending but also a couple more experienced students. To make the talk a bit interesting for them as well I said that an equivalence of categories is the correct notion of “sameness” of categories, and not isomorphisms due to the fact that categories naturally lie in a $2$-category.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The homotopy litmus test</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-litmus-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-litmus-test/</guid>
      <description>A litmus test is a question asked in politics to a potential candidate for high office in which the answer determines if the person gets nominated or not. If a person or a committee holds the power of nominating candidates, they can use that power to make sure that a potential candidate holds their view on a certain matter. So, what does this have to do with mathematics, or especially with homotopy theory?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under category</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/under-category/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/under-category/</guid>
      <description>Since one of my main mathematical interests is homotopy theory, im bound to often bump into things that require the use of base-points. This has long been the classical way to study spaces, especially in terms of homotopy groups. When I was introduced to these so-called pointed spaces, I couldn’t help but feel that these we less natural, or more ad hoc, than regular spaces. I didn’t know much about categories then, but have since learned it is usually in this context that some form of naturality occur.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the cosmos: Properties and definition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/defining-the-cosmos-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/defining-the-cosmos-2/</guid>
      <description>This post is part two of a little two-part miniseries about defining the cosmos. To learn what a cosmos is in mathematics, or rather what we want it to be, you can read the first part. There we described a cosmos as a nice place to enrich a category, or a nice place to do enriched category theory, and to quickly recap, an enriched category is a category where we have objects of morphisms instead of just a collection of them, and these objects come from some monoidal category.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the cosmos: Enriched category theory</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/defining-the-cosmos-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/defining-the-cosmos-1/</guid>
      <description>I think there are many parts of physics worth studying for mathematicians, and the physical notion of a cosmos may be one of them, but, this post is not about physics. Even though the usual field of study one thinks of when hearing the word “cosmos” is physics, there is also a type of mathematical object with the same name. This type of object does have that name for a reason, which is not clear maybe from the object it self, but from what one can do with and in such an object.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Warsaw circle</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-warsaw-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-warsaw-circle/</guid>
      <description>The last few posts have all been of relatively long length and have all taken some time to construct and write. I initially also wanted to produce shorter posts just discussing an example or a calculation etc, and today I tried to do just that, but failed. The post became somewhat longer than intended, but it is really informal and intuitive, so its fine in my opinion.
In a previous post we discussed both weak homotopy equivalences and regular homotopy equivalences, and we have also encountered the Whitehead theorem, which says that any weak homotopy equivalence between CW-complexes is in fact a regular homotopy equivalence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/orbifolds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/orbifolds/</guid>
      <description>For quite some time I have occasionally stumbled onto the Wikipedia page for orbifolds while looking at topology related mathematics. I have always been fascinated by them, and always though that they certainly will come up during studies at university, but they never have (at least not yet). On said wikipedia page it says that the word orbifold is short for “orbit manifold” and that these orbifolds are in fact a generalization of manifolds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sheaves</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/sheaves/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/sheaves/</guid>
      <description>This summer I’m participating in Ravi Vakils pseudocourse on algebraic geometry, AGITTOC. Hence this summer serves as a wonderful opportunity to learn and write about cool mathematics. For long I have wanted to dive deeper into this abstract topic after just dipping my toes in during my bachelor thesis, and now it is time. Ravi though us in the first lecture that we shouldn’t study abstract objects without a cause, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swan&#39;s theorem</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</guid>
      <description>A part of mathematics I really an starting to enjoy more is mathematics that explain or develop connections between geometry or topology, and algebra. The first two posts on this blog was focused on developing some geometrical insight to two lemmas from commutative algebra, namely Noether’s normalization lemma and Zariski’s lemma. There are many more such connections worth discussing and exploring, and today I want to focus on one of these “bridges” between geometry and algebra, namely Swan’s theorem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The homotopy category</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-category/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-category/</guid>
      <description>This is part 9 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
Last time we ended by giving a definition of a homotopy between maps on the collection of bifibrant objects in a model category. Today we are going to expand further upon this idea, and try to build the theory we are familiar with for topological spaces but in the general setting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy in model categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-in-model-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-in-model-categories/</guid>
      <description>This is part 8 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
Last time we finally defined the model category, gave some examples and tried (kind of) to give a motivation to why they are interesting and how they set the stage for homotopy theory. The first time I read the definition I was a bit confused about the lack of mention of homotopy, or at least some prototype of it that I could connect with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/model-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/model-categories/</guid>
      <description>This is part 7 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
Finally we have made it to the destination we set, namely, more abstraction. This post is focused on the definition and intuition on model categories, which abstracts the objects we have been studying for some weeks, namely fibrations and cofibrations. The main definition is that of a model structure on a category, which together with a nice category will form the definition of a model category.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cofibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 6 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
Through the series so far we have covered the basic uses of fibrations and related things, like the long exact sequence of homotopy groups, the Serre spectral sequence, fiber bundles and homotopy groups of spheres. But, we have not mentioned that fibrations has a dual construct, namely cofibrations. The road we are heading with this series, as mentioned before, is to define Model categories, and discover how to use them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanging pictures with homotopy</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/hanging-pictures-with-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/hanging-pictures-with-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago I saw this problem of hanging a picture on the wall using a string and two nails in such a way that if you remove one of the nails from the wall, the picture falls down. This is a bad way to hang pictures you immediately say, and I would agree. I saw some solution to the problem, and didn’t think about it for many years, until this week when I figured out that we need homotopy, in particular the fundamental group, to do it!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A homotopy group of a sphere</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</guid>
      <description>This is part 5 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
As promised in the previous part, we are going to calculate $\pi_4(S^3)$. I think we will have to use all of the machinery (plus some new) that we have been through during this series to do the calculation. What more could we possibly need you ask? Last time we developed the machinery to calculate the cohomology of the total space of a fibration, but we want to compute homotopy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Serre spectral sequence</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</guid>
      <description>This is part 4 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
My personal favorite part about fibrations is that they come equipped with a natural way to compute the cohomology of the total space from the cohomology of the base and the cohomology of the fibers. This process is encoded in a structure called a spectral sequence, and is a complicated object in its full generality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy groups</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
For an introduction to the material, the definitions, motivation and some examples, please read part 1 and part 2 about fibrations and fiber bundles. This and the the following parts of this series will be about their usefulness, especially in computing homology and homotopy groups. This will be done through two different techniques, namely the long exact sequence of homotopy groups, and the spectral sequence associated to a fibration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fiber bundles</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
Yesterday we discussed the standard definition of a fibration by the homotopy lifting property, and today we are continuing that discussion, but in a more visual manner. This we will do by first looking at fiber bundles, and then generalizing them. Since fibrations are generalized fiber bundles, every fiber bundle is an example of a fibration, and they have been the most important examples for me, as they help me visualize and get intuition into the fibrations without having to really use the full generality of the definition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
My main mathematical interest for the last couple years has been algebraic topology. I feel it suits my needs for intuition, and graphical picturing of what happens. A concept I have been learning more rigorously recently is fibrations, and how to use them in computing homotopy groups and homology groups of different spaces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More geometric intuition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/more-geometric-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/more-geometric-intuition/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I wrote a geometric explanation of Noether’s normalization lemma, which you can find here. I’m going to use the geometric machinery developed in that post, so it can be useful to read that first.
One useful result that is often stated as a corollary to Noether’s normalization lemma is Zariski’s lemma. It is a corollary of the algebraic form of the normalization lemma, so i thought there ought to be a geometric version of it as well, which I think I have found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geometric intuition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/geometric-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/geometric-intuition/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This spring I have been taking a graduate class in commutative algebra, and I have yet to do algebraic geometry in a proper way, and have only gotten a small taste while writing my bachelor thesis. So this entire semester, I have felt this hinting at a geometric picture from the algebra itself, but i didn&amp;rsquo;t have the insight to figure it out. That said, I now think I have the geometric picture for Noether normalization, which in term implies a geometric picture of Hilbert nullstellensatz and some other results.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
