<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Localization on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/localization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Localization on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/localization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stable infinity-categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/stable-infinity-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2022/stable-infinity-categories/</guid>
      <description>This semester I am taking part in a seminar on $\infty$-categories, administered by Rune Haugseng. So far we have covered roughly: the basic definitions, fibrations, limits, colimits, Joyal’s lifting theorem, equivalences, straightening, Yoneda lemma, adjunctions and Kan extensions. This week it is my turn to give a talk on stable $\infty$-categories, and this blog post will hopefully be some sort of lecture notes for this talk. The intersection of things in this post and the contents of the talk should at least be non-empty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bousfield localization</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/bousfield-localization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/bousfield-localization/</guid>
      <description>Topology, particularly homotopy theory, is hard. The scenes where these kind of mathematics happen are immensely complicated; the category of topological spaces; the category of spectra. The problem is that there is simply too much information to try to capture by using simple tools that we can actually understand properly. Trying to classify topological spaces or spectra is a feat that many deem impossible, it is simply too difficult.
So, how can we try to fix this?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
