<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Category theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>/categories/category-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Category theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/category-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Lecture in My Second Year</title>
      <link>/posts/2021/a-leqture-in-my-second-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2021/a-leqture-in-my-second-year/</guid>
      <description>For those that don’t know I am a fifth year mathematics student at NTNU, meaning I am finishing my masters degree after this semester. During my time at NTNU I have had some wonderful classes, and some wonderful teachers. Since most I post about on this blog is related to topology, it is very safe to assume that some of my most memorable courses are exactly the topology courses. I very recently looked at my notes from my first topology course, or rather one of the two first, as I took two in parallel during my fourth semester.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swans Theorem</title>
      <link>/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</guid>
      <description>A part of mathematics I really an starting to enjoy more is mathematics that explain or develop connections between geometry or topology, and algebra. The first two posts on this blog was focused on developing some geometrical insight to two lemmas from commutative algebra, namely Noether’s normalization lemma and Zariski’s lemma. There are many more such connections worth discussing and exploring, and today I want to focus on one of these “bridges” between geometry and algebra, namely Swan’s theorem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model categories</title>
      <link>/posts/2020/model-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020/model-categories/</guid>
      <description>This is part 7 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 8 and 9.
Finally we have made it to the destination we set, namely, more abstraction. This post is focused on the definition and intuition on model categories, which abstracts the objects we have been studying for some weeks, namely fibrations and cofibrations. The main definition is that of a model structure on a category, which together with a nice category will form the definition of a model category.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
