<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hopf fibration on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/hopf-fibration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hopf fibration on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/hopf-fibration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The homotopy groups of the spheres. Part 1</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-groups-of-spheres/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-groups-of-spheres/</guid>
      <description>Recently I gave a talk about the homotopy groups of spheres, and as usual, I try to collect my thoughts on this blog before (or after) presenting. The homotopy groups of spheres have featured several times on this blog, and we have made some effort into calculating them for some small dimensions. In the talk I wanted to showcase some methods used to calculate these groups, as well as doing some of the &amp;ldquo;calculations&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Serre spectral sequence</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</guid>
      <description>This is part 4 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
My personal favorite part about fibrations is that they come equipped with a natural way to compute the cohomology of the total space from the cohomology of the base and the cohomology of the fibers. This process is encoded in a structure called a spectral sequence, and is a complicated object in its full generality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy groups</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see the series overview.
For an introduction to the material, the definitions, motivation and some examples, please read part 1 and part 2 about fibrations and fiber bundles. This and the the following parts of this series will be about their usefulness, especially in computing homology and homotopy groups. This will be done through two different techniques, namely the long exact sequence of homotopy groups, and the spectral sequence associated to a fibration.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
