<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adapted homology on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/series/adapted-homology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adapted homology on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/series/adapted-homology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Exotic algebraic models</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2024/exotic-algebraic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2024/exotic-algebraic-models/</guid>
      <description>This blog-post is dedicated to this day, $\pi$-day (14th of march), where we celebrate $\pi_*$, the stable homotopy groups.
As has been the case a couple of times already, when faced with an increased workload I tend to neglect writing on this blog. It is only natural that increased amounts of work in one section lead to a decreased amount of work in another — there is, after all, only a finite amount of time given to us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hopf algebroids</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/hopf-algebroids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/hopf-algebroids/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In the last blog post we introduced and studied adapted homology theories. Given a stable $\infty$-category $\mathcal{C}$ and $\mathcal{A}$ an abelian category with enough injectives together with a local grading $[1]\colon \mathcal{A}\longrightarrow \mathcal{A}$, an adapted homology theory is a functor
$$ H\colon \mathcal{C}\longrightarrow \mathcal{A} $$
such that $H$ is additive, sends fiber sequences to long exact sequences, sends the suspension $\Sigma$ of $\mathcal{C}$ to the shift $[1]$ of $\mathcal{A}$ and such that we can lift injectives in $\mathcal{A}$ into $\mathcal{C}$ through $H$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapted homology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/adapted-homology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/adapted-homology/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In the last post we studied homology theories as abstract functors from stable $\infty$-categories to abelian categories. We showed that for every stable $\infty$-category $\mathcal{C}$ there is a universal homology theory which all others factor through, namely the Yoneda embedding into the Freyd envelope,
$$ y\colon \mathcal{C}\longrightarrow A(\mathcal{C}). $$
The fact that this is universal means that for any homology theory $H\colon \mathcal{C}\longrightarrow \mathcal{A}$ there is an essentially unique factorization</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universal homology</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/universal-homology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2023/universal-homology/</guid>
      <description>New year; same me; new math. During the fall I said that I wanted to post on this blog monthly, but that did not happen for some reason. I thought I’d try again this semester, but maybe I am setting this not that high bar still too high for my self. For some reason there seems to be fewer hours in the day than it used to. The cover page for the post is generated by Dalle·2 using the prompt &amp;ldquo;A man finding the universal piece, old painting&amp;rdquo; – a true work of art.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
